<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | Chris Arriola]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-01T18:30:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisarriola.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Arriola]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Last Week in San Diego]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2012/02/21/last-week-in-san-diego/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2012/02/21/last-week-in-san-diego</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:center;"><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/torreypines2_sandiego.jpg"><img class="aligncenter" title="Torrey Pines" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/torreypines2_sandiego.jpg?w=300" alt="" width="300" height="225" /></a></p>


<p>It&rsquo;s officially my last week of living here in San Diego. It&rsquo;s been a tremendous experience and it&rsquo;s hard to believe I&rsquo;m leaving this piece of paradise (I&rsquo;m going to miss you yearlong mid-70 degree weather)!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve always been a huge advocate of goal-setting and having the end in mind. To me, if one is compelled by a vision, then one must make the steps to fulfill that vision. This entails making all the necessary changes to get to the end point. Every action, I view, should be a result of striving for a larger goal. No matter the difficulty of the action, if it is necessary, it must be made. Failure to do so, makes all the difference between getting what you want, and what you don&rsquo;t want.</p>

<p>With that said, zooming out 10,000 feet and putting into perspective the bigger picture, for me to achieve my long-term goals, I need to make the necessary steps in the present to get to where I want to be. At the moment, that means leaving the confines of HP and joining an exciting startup in the bay area. Startups and social innovation have always fascinated me and it only makes sense for me to move towards that direction. Personally, I find it easy to get sucked into something simply because it&rsquo;s interesting or comforting. However, I know that for me to feel a sense of fulfillment, I need look beyond the mist and act in accordance to my goals and follow my passion. Even if that means leaving something as beautiful as San Diego.</p>

<p>Farewell, San Diego. You will be severely missed!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mount Roraima]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/07/09/mount-roraima/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/07/09/mount-roraima</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_169&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;300&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Mount Roraima &ndash; Venezuela&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/mount_roraima_venezuela1.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-169 " title="Mount_Roraima_Venezuela1" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/mount_roraima_venezuela1.jpg?w=300&h=221" alt="" width="300" height="221" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_170&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;300&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Mount Roraima &mdash; Venezuela&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/247503xcitefun-mount-roraima1.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-170" title="247503,xcitefun-mount-roraima1" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/07/247503xcitefun-mount-roraima1.jpg?w=300&h=201" alt="" width="300" height="201" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The highest tepui plateau (table-top surface) of the Pacaraima Mountains &mdash; Mount Roraima. It&rsquo;s surrounded by 400 meter tall cliffs and most of the environment on the summit is rock. Despite minute resources such as soil, plants and animals THRIVE in this environment. Many of which, if not all, only exist on Mount Roraima. <a href="http://www.crunchgear.com/2009/10/16/the-crazy-rolling-pebble-toad/">CHECK OUT THIS TOAD</a>!!!</p>

<p>This habitat is truly a &ldquo;lost world.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photoshop Power]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/03/29/photoshop-power/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/03/29/photoshop-power</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve always been disappointed with the photos I take whenever I go travel. For instance, when I went on a roadtrip from NJ to CA the photos did not do the actual sights any justice. So I decided to save up some cash and purchase an SLR—I&rsquo;m getting the Canon rebel t2i next week!!! However, as it turns out, photography is not all about the camera, it&rsquo;s also about the post-modifications you make to your images. Anyway, I was messing around with photoshop lately and I really wanted to tweak this image I had of torrey pines in San Diego. It was a nice shot but it had poor lighting. Here&rsquo;s the before and after photos:</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_131&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;1024&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Torrey Pines &ndash; Before Photo&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc03897.jpg"><img class="size-large wp-image-131" title="Torrey Pines - Before Photo" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc03897.jpg?w=1024" alt="" width="1024" height="768" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_132&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;1024&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Torrey Pines &ndash; After Photo&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc03897-editted.jpg"><img class="size-large wp-image-132" title="Torrey Pines - After Photo" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc03897-editted.jpg?w=1024" alt="" width="1024" height="768" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p style="text-align:left;">I basically adjusted hue, saturation, and lighting. Pretty cool huh? I know it might be overkill but I like it. =]</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rendezvous Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/03/25/rendezvous-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/03/25/rendezvous-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_138&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;1024&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Red Rock Rendezvous &ndash; Chris, Elaine, and I&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc037771.jpg"><img class="size-large wp-image-138" title="Red Rock Rendezvous" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/dsc037771.jpg?w=1024" alt="" width="1024" height="768" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Two of my good friends from NJ stayed over to visit me in San Diego last week. It was a pretty action-packed week filled with epic adventures around SoCal and Vegas. Over the weekend, we actually went to a rock climbing festival at the Red Rock Canyon in Vegas called the <em>Red Rock Rendezvous.</em> It&rsquo;s the biggest climbing event in the US that&rsquo;s hosted by mountaingear yearly. Climbers from all around the country come and gather to socialize, eat, drink beer, learn more about climbing, and of course&hellip; CLIMB!</p>

<p>Last weekend was actually my first time climbing outdoors; I also haven&rsquo;t camped outside in years, and I must say&hellip; the whole experience of driving to Vegas, staying in a tent, meeting people with similar interests, and climbing a frikin' canyon was such a life-changing experience. Yes, life-changing (I&rsquo;m not exaggerating). What made the experience even more interesting was the fact that our first night there was literally the windiest night ever. As we were trying to sleep in our tent we could hear the wind rushing over the canyon, and after a few seconds, that same wind would twist our tent it in many different directions (the roof kept hitting my friend in the face). It felt like the end of the world. As we stepped out of our tent at 6am with about an hour of sleep—it was still windy—many campers left and decided to stay at hotels, others lost their tent cause of the wind, while the lucky few still had their tents up. Yeah&hellip; we were one of them! Ironically, although the climbing, drinking, socializing, hiking, etc. was really fun, that night was actually my favorite part of the trip. At that moment of misery (at least what others would consider as misery), although my body was yearning for sleep my mind kept me wide awake and well aware of what was happening. Yes it was windy, but at that moment I couldn&rsquo;t help but smile and think to myself—"Wow, this is AWESOME!&ldquo; It was that feeling of a newly found hobby that I can truly find myself being passionate about—not only for a few days, but for my entire life. I was ecstatic. Climb on!!!!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smuggler's Cove]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/02/19/smugglers-cove/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2011/02/19/smugglers-cove</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_106&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;300&rdquo; caption=&ldquo;Smugglers Cove&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/smugglers-cove.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-106 " title="Smuggler's Cove, Greece" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/smugglers-cove.jpg?w=300" alt="" width="300" height="199" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Navagio Beach (Smuggler&rsquo;s Cove) in Greece. A smuggler ship wreck called Panagiotis still sits by the bay&mdash;how bad ass is that?!? Sounds like a future destination point!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
