<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Patterns, | Chris Arriola]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/categories/patterns/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-02T23:34:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisarriola.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Arriola]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Like a Goldfish]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2015/10/18/code-like-a-goldfish/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-18T16:46:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2015/10/18/code-like-a-goldfish</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is an underlying hidden requirement in creating software products. It doesn&rsquo;t just have to &ldquo;work&rdquo;; it needs to be molded in such a way that it can be changed, maintained, and scaled easily.</p>

<p>Last month, I gave a talk addressing this topic to the 1st cohort at <a href="http://www.telegraphacademy.com/">Telegraph Academy</a>—an  immersive program that teaches underrepresented groups in tech on how to code. They were nearing their last week of the program so I thought it would be relevant to share some industry lessons.</p>

<p><strong>TL;DR</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><p>Design early</p>

<p> The biggest mistake beginners tend to make is not taking the time to think through the pros/cons of a software design. Designing early makes it easier to find flaws, it&rsquo;s much harder fixing those flaws once it&rsquo;s expressed in code.</p></li>
<li><p>Don&rsquo;t over optimize</p>

<p> This doesn&rsquo;t just apply to algorithms (e.g. trying to get O(n * log n) performance vs O(n<sup>2</sup>) on a small dataset), but it also applies to software design. Don&rsquo;t over-engineer or over-genericize a problem if it doesn&rsquo;t have to be.</p></li>
<li><p>Don&rsquo;t repeat yourself (DRY)</p>

<p> Code repetition means if something needs to be changed/fixed, it needs to be changed in all parts of the code which is error-prone. Have one source of truth and abstract where appropriate.</p></li>
<li><p>Think small</p>

<p> Smaller classes, methods, and files are easier to maintain.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Check out the slides <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/arriolac/code-like-a-goldfish">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
