<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Android | Chris Arriola]]></title>
  <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/categories/android/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-18T14:24:06-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://arriolac.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Arriola]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Preparing for a Hackathon (A Mobile Perspective)]]></title>
    <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2013/07/23/preparing-for-a-hackathon-a-mobile-perspective/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2013/07/23/preparing-for-a-hackathon-a-mobile-perspective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2013/07/536444_10150917662022200_1083819652_a.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image  " id="i-461" alt="Image" align="middle" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2013/07/536444_10150917662022200_1083819652_a.jpg?w=170" width="170" height="261" /></a></p>

<p dir="ltr">The time-pressure imposed at hackathons make it essential for teams to prepare ahead of time so that they can focus on the most critical tasks (building the actual product) the day of the event. Typically though, hackers come in without a team or idea. Whether you fall under this category or not, <em>preparation is still important</em>. Given that a full-blown business and a polished working product is unlikely to be built overnight, the point of a hackathon should be to learn as much as you can as well as form long-lasting relationships with people in your team—<strong>the burning desire for building and creating new things does not stop after a weekend</strong>!</p>


<p dir="ltr">Let’s say you do have a team and an idea to work on over the course of a sleep-deprived weekend. So where should you start? I thought I’d share some mobile-specific (Android and iOS) tools and projects you can leverage to bootstrap the development process.</p>




<h3>Back-end</h3>


<p dir="ltr">If you want to do data-persistence you can always build your own server logic, create RESTful APIs and create database schemas, but if you want a simple back-end service solution, the best option right now is to use <a title="Parse" href="www.parse.com" target="_blank">Parse</a>. <em>Parse</em> allows you to create models in a nice visual dashboard and then automatically creates a RESTful API for you to do CRUD operations on that model. Best of all, <em>Parse</em> is free until you hit a million requests on the API which is something you don’t have to worry about in a hackathon setting. In short, if you’re building a mobile app and you don’t have a dedicated server guy, go with <em>Parse</em>.</p>




<h3>Networking</h3>


<p dir="ltr">If you’re going to be integrating with some sort of web service (Facebook, Twitter, etc.), chances are, you’ll be using their APIs. Perhaps you might build your own API. Regardless, client-side you’ll need a pretty solid networking library to use. iOS and Android have their native implementations but you’ll be better of using a 3rd party library with a much simpler API that abstracts all the nitty-gritty details of HTTP. For iOS, <a title="AFNetworking" href="https://github.com/AFNetworking/AFNetworking" target="_blank">AFNetworking</a> and <a title="RestKit" href="https://github.com/RestKit/RestKit" target="_blank">RestKit</a> (uses <em>AFNetworking</em>) are the common solutions, whereas for Android, you have a couple of options but to name a few <a title="OkHTTP" href="https://github.com/square/okhttp" target="_blank">OkHTTP</a>, <a title="Retrofit" href="http://square.github.io/retrofit/" target="_blank">Retrofit</a> and <a title="android-async-http" href="https://github.com/loopj/android-async-http" target="_blank">android-async-http</a> are pretty solid.</p>




<h3>Convenience Libraries</h3>


<p dir="ltr">Do you make common mistakes on Android such as forgetting to check for <em>null</em>? Do you have the issue of stale objects such as Fragments and/or Activities when doing callbacks? A couple of ways to get around that is to use <a title="Guava" href="https://code.google.com/p/guava-libraries/" target="_blank">Guava</a> which has a lot of convenience classes that for Java, and to use some sort of event bus such as Square’s <a title="Otto" href="https://github.com/square/otto" target="_blank">Otto</a> to avoid callback nightmare.</p>


<p dir="ltr">Hopefully these tools help you with your next Hackathon. If you have any suggestions/tips please feel free to leave a comment. Keep hacking!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android Security Part 1 - Reverse Engineering Android Apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/08/31/android-security-part-1-reverse-engineering-android-apps/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/08/31/android-security-part-1-reverse-engineering-android-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Google introduced automatic support for <strong>ProGuard</strong>, a code obfuscation tool, in ADT as early as December 2010 in version 8.0.0. It is integrated into the build system to make code obfuscation a pretty "straightforward" process. Since then, Google has encouraged—albeit not proactively—developers to enable ProGuard to prevent hackers from reverse engineering and hacking applications. Despite enabling ProGuard, however, a very persistent hacker may still be able to reverse engineer a ProGuard-ed application but the task becomes exponentially harder. There are other good practices developers should abide by to ensure a secure app, but code obfuscation should always be the first line of defense (more information on code obfuscation on Android <a title="ProGuard" href="http://android-developers.blogspot.com/2010/09/proguard-android-and-licensing-server.html">here</a> and <a title="ProGuard 2" href="http://android-developers.blogspot.com/2010/09/securing-android-lvl-applications.html">here</a>).

Out of curiosity, I went ahead and did some reverse engineering on some popular apps (all have more than 1 million downloads on Google Play) that may contain user sensitive information and un/surprisingly, 10 out of 12 weren't doing some sort of code obfuscation. I'm sharing in this post what and how I did that to point out 2 things: (1) how easy it is to reverse engineer an app, and (2) to increase awareness of the importance of security specifically code obfuscation.
</p>




<h3>Methodology</h3>


<p>My methodology was simple, in fact, a quick Google Search on &ldquo;<em>Android Hacking</em>&rdquo; should give anyone the tools to do this. Below are the steps:</p>

<ol>
    <li>Obtain the .apk files of the applications of interest by using <em>Astro File Manager</em>. Simply navigate to "tools" in the options menu, "Application Backup", and then select all the apps you're interested in. Once backup is perform, an image is obtained of the apps and the corresponding .apk files will be stored under your SD card's <em>backups/</em> directory.</li>
    <li>Unpack .apk file using <em>unzip</em>.</li>
    <li>Disassemble compiled <em>classes.dex</em> file using <a title="smali/baksmali" href="http://code.google.com/p/smali/">baksmali</a>. This will generate tons of .smali files.</li>
    <li>Perform static analysis on .smali files.</li>
</ol>


<p>For step 4, if an application does not have code obfuscation, then all static constant declarations can be read in plain text (<span style="color:#ff0000;">red flag</span>!). You can still take things a step further, for instance, by writing smali code and retracing your steps to create your own custom hacked-out app.</p>

<h3>Results</h3>


<p>Understanding <em>smali</em> code is pretty straightforward event without prior knowledge of the language especially when it comes to finding static member fields. Declared String values are human-readable.</p>

<p>Here are a few screen-shots of what I&rsquo;ve found:</p>

<br />


<p><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-435" title="Key 1" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret.png" alt="" width="510" height="22" /></a> Fig. 1
<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret2.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-434" title="Key 2" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret2.png" alt="" width="510" height="37" /></a> Fig. 2
<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret3.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-433" title="Key 3" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret3.png" alt="" width="510" height="26" /></a> Fig. 3
<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret4.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-432" title="secret4" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/secret4.png" alt="" width="510" height="16" /></a> Fig. 4</p>

<br />




<h3>Conclusion</h3>


<p>ProGuard creates drastic improvements in security. Here&rsquo;s an example of how smali code would look like with ProGuard on vs. with ProGuard off.</p>

<p>Say your <em>Activity </em>has a static member field <em>HACK_THIS</em>:<br /></p>

<p><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/java-code1.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-444" title="java-code" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/java-code1.png" alt="" width="510" height="320" /></a> Fig. 5<br /></p>

<p>When we disassemble the resulting .dex file without ProGuard enabled, we get this:</p>

<p><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/proguarded.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-442" title="ProGuarded" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/proguarded.png" alt="" width="510" height="484" /></a> Fig. 6<br /></p>

<p>Whereas code obfuscation using ProGuard results in:</p>

<p><a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/proguarded1.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-449" title="proguarded" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/08/proguarded1.png" alt="" width="510" height="485" /></a><br /></p>

<p>From this comparison, you can observe the following: enabling ProGuard in this situation removes the human-readable static member field whereas disabling it leaves it in plain-text in smali assembly code. Although the content of the String gets copied wherever it is used in code as seen on line 39 in Figure 7, the context of what that String represents is virtually unknown. Again, a persistent hacker may deduce what that means through brute-force, but ProGuard increases the complexity of the task.</p>

<h4>#</h4>

<p>Any tips on how to create a secure Android app? Leave a comment below!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android: Capture and Crop an Image]]></title>
    <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/07/18/android-capture-and-crop-an-image/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/07/18/android-capture-and-crop-an-image</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One line: Intent cropIntent = <span style="color:#3366ff;"><strong>new</strong></span> Intent(<span style="color:#0000ff;">&ldquo;com.android.camera.action.CROP&rdquo;</span>);</p>

<p>Great tutorial from mobile tuts+: <a href="http://mobile.tutsplus.com/tutorials/android/capture-and-crop-an-image-with-the-device-camera/"><a href="http://mobile.tutsplus.com/tutorials/android/capture-and-crop-an-image-with-the-device-camera/">http://mobile.tutsplus.com/tutorials/android/capture-and-crop-an-image-with-the-device-camera/</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic Data with ListView + Loading Footer]]></title>
    <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/06/15/dynamic-data-with-listview-loading-footer/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/06/15/dynamic-data-with-listview-loading-footer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A pretty common UI design pattern for  ListViews on Android is displaying a loading footer for the dynamic loading of a list. It&rsquo;s a pattern used by several well known apps &ndash; Twitter, Gmail and Instagram to mention a few &ndash; to display data without having to click a button to paginate through information. Essentially, as a user scrolls down to the end of a list, which indicates the end of the current page, a loading indicator is displayed at the footer of the list to notify the user that the list is in the process of populating more data.</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_389&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;510&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/dynamiclist.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-389" title="Dynamic List" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/dynamiclist.png" alt="" width="510" height="340" /></a> Dynamic Loading of a List (<a href="http://www.androidpatterns.com/uap_pattern/dynamic-loading-of-a-list"><a href="http://www.androidpatterns.com/uap_pattern/dynamic-loading-of-a-list">http://www.androidpatterns.com/uap_pattern/dynamic-loading-of-a-list</a></a>)[/caption]</p>

<p>While playing around with this pattern, I was quite surprise how not-so-straightforward it was to implement this (then again, that&rsquo;s programming for you). With that said, I&rsquo;d like to share my implementation with you in case you&rsquo;re trying to use this pattern in your application.</p>

<h3>Trial 1</h3>


<p>The intuitive way to go about this is to (1) simply attach an Adapter with the first page of items to a ListView, (2) attach an OnScrollListener to detect if the bottom of the list has been reached, if so, (3) add a loading footer view to the list while retrieving more data, and when the retrieval process is done, remove the loading footer and (4) update the adapter with the recently pulled data.</p>

<p>Sounds pretty straightforward right? Turns out, it&rsquo;s not.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s some code snippets of the above approach.</p>

<p>(1) &amp; (2)</p>

<pre>ListView list = (ListView) findViewById(R.id.listview);
MyAdapter adapter = new MyAdapter(context, items);
list.setAdapter(adapter);

list.setOnScrollListener(new OnScrollListener() {
    @Override
    public void onScrollStateChanged(AbsListView view, 
            int scrollState) {
         <span style="color:#339966;">// Do nothing</span>
    }

    @Override
    public void onScroll(AbsListView view, int firstVisibleItem, 
            int visibleItemCount, int totalItemCount) {

        <span style="color:#339966;">// threshold being indicator if bottom of list is hit</span>
        if (firstVisibleItem = threshold) {
            pullMoreData();
        }
    }
});</pre>


<p>(3) &amp; (4)</p>

<pre>private void pullMoreData() {
    doNetworkRequest(page); <span style="color:#339966;">// Perform request for next page</span>
    list.addFooterView(loadingFooter);
}

@Override
public void onNetworkRequestComplete(Request request) {
    list.removeFooterView(loadingFooter);
    adapter.addAll(request.getData());
    adapter.notifyDataSetChanged();
}</pre>


<p>This implementation, however, does not result in the intended action &ndash; the footer never gets displayed. A work-around I did for this leads me to&hellip;</p>

<h3>Trial 2</h3>


<p>With my second trial, I did this: (1) attached the footer first before the adapter, and when the bottom of the list has been reached and new data has been retrieved, (2) reattach the footer and create a new adapter with the old+new data which is then reattached to the list. Finally, to bring the user back to the scroll position, I (3) keep track of the first visible item on the scroll view and set the list selection to be this item.</p>

<p>Immediately, a few things must be popping up in your head such as: that must be slow! it&rsquo;s a hack! there has to be a cleaner way! etc. I can&rsquo;t agree with you more.</p>

<p>(1), (2) &amp; (3)</p>

<pre>ListView list = (ListView) findViewById(R.id.listview);
list.addFooterView(loadingFooter);

MyAdapter adapter = new MyAdapter(context, items);
list.setAdapter(adapter);

list.setOnScrollListener(new OnScrollListener() {
    @Override
    public void onScrollStateChanged(AbsListView view, 
            int scrollState) {
         <span style="color:#339966;">// Do nothing</span>
    }

    @Override
    public void onScroll(AbsListView view, int firstVisibleItem, 
            int visibleItemCount, int totalItemCount) {

<span style="color:#339966;"> // member variable for restoring selection</span>
        mSelection = firstVisibleItem;

<span style="color:#339966;"> // threshold being indicator if bottom of list is hit</span>
        if (firstVisibleItem = threshold) {
            pullMoreData();
        }
    }
});

@Override
public void onNetworkRequestComplete(Request request) {
    list.removeFooterView(loadingFooter);
    list.addFooterView(loadingFooter);

    MyAdapter newAdapter = new MyAdapter(this);
    newAdapter.addOldData(adapter);
    newAdapter.addAll(request.getData());

    list.setAdapter(newAdapter);
    adapter = newAdapter;

<span style="color:#339966;"> // Set table to last selection</span>
    list.setSelection(mSelection)
}</pre>


<p>Albeit some performance issues and jerkiness because of (3), this implementation actually works.</p>

<p>Can we do better than this?</p>

<h3>Trial 3</h3>


<p>The trick, it turns out, is to <strong>attach the footer view before setting the adapter</strong>, this way, any combination of adding and removing of the footer view/s just works. <strong>Why does it have to be in order</strong>!? If you have the answer, please leave a comment. I&rsquo;d love to know</p>

<pre>ListView list = (ListView) findViewById(R.id.listview);
list.addFooterView(loadingFooter);

MyAdapter adapter = new MyAdapter(context, items);
list.setAdapter(adapter);

<span style="color:#339966;">// this step is important to not display the footer view // right of the bat.</span>
list.removeFooterView(loadingFooter);

list.setOnScrollListener(new OnScrollListener() {
    @Override
    public void onScrollStateChanged(AbsListView view, 
            int scrollState) {
<span style="color:#339966;"> // Do nothing</span>
    }

    @Override
    public void onScroll(AbsListView view, int firstVisibleItem, 
            int visibleItemCount, int totalItemCount) {
<span style="color:#339966;"> // threshold being indicator if bottom of list is hit</span>
        if (firstVisibleItem = threshold) {
            pullMoreData();
        }
    }
});</pre>


<p>I&rsquo;ll share more Android quirks as they come up, I hope this helped.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Optimizing Android Layouts]]></title>
    <link href="http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/05/23/optimizing-android-layouts/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://arriolac.github.io/blog/2012/05/23/optimizing-android-layouts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently used the <strong>hierarchyviewer</strong> &amp; <strong>lint </strong>tool in the Android SDK and was pretty surprised with the results I saw. Many of the views I had were heavily nested and some views did not necessarily have to be inflated off the bat (progress indicators and refresh icons to name a few). As a result, my activity took a performance hit because of a badly designed layout.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a technique I used that I picked up at AnDevCon III to flatten my layouts and in general make them more performant.</p>

<h3><strong>ViewStub</strong></h3>


<p>Essentially, ViewStub is a lightweight and cheap to inflate widget that you can include in a layout. Its purpose is basically to serve as a stub or placeholder for views that don&rsquo;t necessarily need to be inflated on creation. For example, let&rsquo;s say your app displays notifications on a SlidingDrawer; however, when there are no notifications, that SlidingDrawer should be hidden. What you can do then is create a ViewStub that points to your SlidingDrawer layout implementation and when notifications are present, you can simply inflate the ViewStub. Here&rsquo;s an example taken from <a href="http://developer.android.com/resources/articles/layout-tricks-stubs.html">Android Developers</a> that displays the flattening of the view hierarchy using ViewStubs.</p>

<p>Layout without ViewStub:</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_341&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;510&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/viewstub41.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-341 " title="Layout Without ViewStub" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/viewstub41.png" alt="" width="510" height="431" /></a> Layout Without ViewStub[/caption]</p>

<p>Layout using ViewStub:</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_342&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;468&rdquo;]<a href="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/viewstub3.png"><img class="size-full wp-image-342 " title="Layout With ViewStub" src="http://chrisarriola.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/viewstub3.png" alt="" width="468" height="476" /></a> Layout With ViewStub[/caption]</p>

<p>The code for your layout:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre><span style="color:#0000ff;">&lt;ViewStub</span>
<span style="color:#ff00ff;">android:id</span>=<span style="color:#339966;">"@+id/stub_slidingdrawer"</span>
<span style="color:#ff00ff;">android:layout</span>=<span style="color:#339966;">"@layout/slidingdrawer"</span>
<span style="color:#ff00ff;">android:layout_width</span>=<span style="color:#339966;">"fill_parent"</span>
<span style="color:#ff00ff;">android:layout_height</span>=<span style="color:#339966;">"wrap_content"</span>
<span style="color:#0000ff;">/&gt;</span></pre>
</blockquote>


<p><span style="color:#0000ff;"><span style="color:#000000;">The code to inflate the ViewStub:</span></span></p>

<blockquote><span style="color:#0000ff;"><span style="color:#000000;">ViewStub stub = (ViewStub) findViewById(R.id.<span style="color:#0000ff;"><em>stub_slidingdrawer</em></span>);</span>
<span style="color:#000000;">View v = stub.inflate();</span> </span></blockquote>


<p>For my specific case, it took about half the time to inflate the entire layout tree by using a ViewStub for infrequently used child layouts. Pretty sweet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
