<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: productivity | Chris Arriola]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-04T17:43:44+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisarriola.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Arriola]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deep Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2014/01/18/deep-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T12:19:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisarriola.me/blog/2014/01/18/deep-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<br/>


<h3>&ldquo;What should I do next to get better at X?&rdquo;</h3>

<br/>


<p><em>Practice&hellip; right?</em></p>

<br/>


<p>When I was in college, I followed a blog by Cal Newport called &ldquo;Study Hacks&rdquo;. If you haven&rsquo;t heard of it yet, I <strong>highly</strong> encourage you to check it out. It changed a lot of my perspectives and some of the lessons I learned I still practice today. Check it out <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/">here</a>.</p>

<p>As I was thinking about the question above, I thought of a topic discussed on <em>Study Hacks</em> called <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2012/11/21/knowledge-workers-are-bad-at-working-and-heres-what-to-do-about-it/">Deep Work</a>.</p>

<p><em>Deep work</em>, according to Cal, is the type of work that causes our abilities to continually improve. It is a source of deeper satisfaction; that is, a feeling of passion towards whatever it is we&rsquo;re pursuing. In contrast, so called <em>shallow work</em> are the types of tasks that require minimal amount of effort. These are the tasks that through repetition and training we&rsquo;re able to do with our eyes closed.</p>

<p>Figuratively, of course.</p>

<p>The answer to the question I posed to myself requires some amount of deep work. With that said, here&rsquo;s how I go about preparing myself for some deep work:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Quiet time</strong></p>

<p> The simple act of turning off all my devices and &ldquo;unplugging&rdquo; myself unleashes tons of creative juices. Distractions from tweets, likes, +1s, e-mails, etc. make it hard to get into any sort of rhythm. Once unplugged, I find that I don&rsquo;t really need to think of anything at all &ndash; ideas just start flowing.</p>

<p> Ironically, some of my most creative moments are in the plane when I&rsquo;m bored out of my mind. Who said boredom was a bad thing??</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Plan for tomorrow</strong></p>

<p> I have trouble maintaining a very rigid routine/schedule. However, it&rsquo;s incredibly easy to plan for the next day. I find that if I just jot down a few reasonable and achievable tasks for myself to do the next day, my mind has time to prepare for what&rsquo;s ahead. Surprisingly, this motivates me to wake up early the following day too.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Be in the now.</strong></p>

<p> The most important part about execution of deep work is to be in the moment. You just need to pay attention to what you&rsquo;re doing. To &ldquo;pay attention&rdquo; is such a great sentiment in this context as it reminds us that attention costs something&hellip; energy.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>How do you prepare yourself for <em>deep work</em>?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
